Finding Aid for Organization for Tropical Studies records, 1948-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Organization for Tropical Studies records 1948-1986, 1958-1979
Organization for Tropical Studies.
10 linear feet
964 Bn 2
Consortium of universities created to study tropical environments focusing on Central America and field activities in tropical habitats. The University of Michigan became a founding member of OTS in April 1963. Administrative records chiefly concerning University of Michigan involvement in the Organization for Tropical Studies and related programs. Records include initial planning documents, committee files, meeting minutes, proposals, reports, topical files and curriculum material. Includes correspondence of Norman Hartweg and Stephen Spurr; also records collected by Warren H. Wagner.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from John Vandermeer (donor 8327 ) in 1995. Additional records came from Florence (Mrs. Warren H.) Wagner (donor no. 9040 ) in 2000. Additional records came from Mark O’Brien (donor no. 837 ) of the Museum of Zoology in 2005. 837
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Organization for Tropical Studies (OTS) was created as a consortium of universities to operate a graduate program in the area of tropical research. The University of Michigan became a founding member of OTS in April 1963.
The organization was officially founded in 1962. The origins of OTS come from a committee at the University of Michigan interested in a proposed center for biological study which began in 1956. In 1958 there were several visits to Mexico as a potential location for the project, but this was later abandoned at the suggestion of Mexican officials. In the fall of 1962 a new committee was formed under professors Norman Hartweg and Stephen Spurr with the idea of bringing together a consortium of universities. Hartweg and Spurr were particularly instrumental in writing the original articles of agreement that led to incorporation in the State of Florida. The by-laws and charter were adopted at another conference in Coral Gables, Florida in February 1963 where Hartweg was elected as the first president of OTS, while Thomas Hubbell also of the University of Michigan faculty served as a member of the Board of Directors.
In March 1963, before becoming a member of OTS, the Michigan Committee on Tropical Studies (MCOTS) was formed. This committee was created to support and promote OTS at the University of Michigan. It was later disbanded.
The purpose of OTS is to further the understanding of the tropics through formal graduate courses and individual research projects in tropical areas. OTS typically has involved about 150 graduate students and 50 faculty members from nearly as many institutions, each year. Funds are obtained through grants from the National Science Foundation as well as other organizations. Emphasis is placed on field instruction, which can be carried on only in tropical environments. Courses are offered in various areas of biology, geography, forestry, earth sciences, biometeorology, and marine sciences. The principle area of concentration has been in Central America, particularly Costa Rica, with a Central American Office located at the University of Costa Rica, and with special agreements for study areas in Guatemala near Escuintla and on the Colombian island of San Andres in the Caribbean. Course offerings emphasize field activities in all of the major tropical habitats where classes meet continuously for periods of one to two weeks. Field locations are selected to provide a spectrum of tropical environments including dry lowlands, wet lowlands, highlands and marine areas. Lodging and field laboratory facilities are arranged through rental of commercial and private establishments, and by a network of permanent field stations.
OTS does not employ a permanent teaching staff. Courses are taught by eminent scientists drawn from the faculties and staffs of universities and scientific organizations throughout the world. A balance of scientific specialities appropriate to each course is provided by two or more faculty members and supporting visiting scientists and local lecturers who are involved for periods which vary from one or two days to several weeks.
Membership to OTS is by institution only. In 1995 there were approximately 50 to 60 member institutions paying an approximate $10,000 annual membership fee, which supports the North American executive offices now located at Duke University.
The records from the Organization for Tropical Studies (OTS) measure 10 linear feet, spanning the years from 1948 to 1986. It is comprised of 13 series: Committee Records; Correspondence; Education Program; Establishment Files; Financial Records; Meeting Files; Membership Records; Projects, Proposals, and Reports; Topical Files, Writings, Files from the office of Warren H. Wagner, and Organizing Committee. There is a related collection of OTS material at Duke University as well as related material located as part of the Stephen H. Spurr papers.
Subjects:
Organization for Tropical Studies.; Biology--Research--Tropics.; Ecology--Research--Tropics.; Ecology--Study and teaching--Field work.; Forest management--Troipcs.; Hartweg, Norman E.; Rain forest ecology.; Rain forests--Costa Rica.; Rain forests--Tropics.; Spurr, Stephen Hopkins.; Wagner, Warren H. (Warren Herbert), 1920-2000
- Committee Records 1959-1984
  The Committee Records (.7 linear feet; 1959-1984) series consists of minutes and correspondences of various committees formed within OTS. The Michigan Committee on Tropical Studies (MCOTS) is included in this series, but the Executive Committee is not because it is part of the Meeting Files series. There are ad hoc and standing committees included. This series is organized alphabetically by the title of the committee.
  - Agricultural Science 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Anthropology 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Associates 1979 (Box 1)
  - Discipline 1970 (Box 1)
  - Earth Science 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Ecosystems Study Control 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Education 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Field Station Regulations 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Forestry 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Geography 1966-1972 (Box 1)
  - Joint OTS-International Biological Programs (IBP) 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Land Acquisitions 1968-1974 (Box 1)
  - Liaison with International Organizations 1972 (Box 1)
  - Marine Sciences 1967-1972 (Box 1)
  - Membership 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Metrology 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Committee on Tropical Studies (MCOTS)
    - Activities 1965-1979 (Box 1)
    - Members 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1964-1979 (Box 1)
  - National Park Services of Costa Rica 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Nominating 1966-1967, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Physical Facilities 1969 (Box 1)
  - Policy 1966 (Box 1)
  - Program Planning 1969-1977, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Publications 1974 (Box 1)
  - Research 1966, 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Service 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Spanish Language Teaching 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Statewide Universities 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Terrestrial Biology 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Tropical Centers 1959 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1963-1986
  The Correspondence (1 linear foot; 1963-1986) series gives the best feeling for the atmosphere of OTS. It includes the correspondence of three OTS presidents, two of which were from the University of Michigan, Thomas Hubbell and Stephen Preston. It is organized chronologically with the exception of selected folders which are ordered alphabetically by correspondent or institution.
  - 1964-1969, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1970-1977, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Campabadal, Jorge R. 1972-1978 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation 1963, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Hubbell, Thomas H. 1965-1979 (Box 2)
  - Preston, Stephen B. 1965-1979 (Box 2)
  - Savage, Jay M. 1974-1979 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan 1964-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Wagner, Warren H. 1977-1986 (Box 2)
- Education Program 1964-1978
  The Education Program series (.7 linear feet; 1964-1978) includes information about the courses offered and related educational concerns. This series contains course announcements, class schedules, correspondence regarding courses offered, course evaluations, and coordinating educational programs with member universities. This series is organized alphabetically.
  - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Activities Schedule 1970 (Box 2)
  - Application for Participation 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Coordinated Education and Research 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Course Coordinators and Teachers 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Courses
    - 1965-1978, 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Advanced Zoology 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - Bibliographies 1969 (Box 3)
    - Biology 1966-1967, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Botany 1966 (Box 3)
    - Costa Rica Information Sheets undated (Box 3)
    - Final Reports 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Forestry 1967-1972 (Box 3)
    - Fundamentals 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Geography 1966 (Box 3)
    - Metrology 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Pine Forests 1972 (Box 3)
  - Latin American Students 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Monthly Seminars 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Program 1974 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Program and Associated Colleges of the Midwest 1973-1974 (Box 3)
- Establishment Files 1956-1970
  Establishment Files (.3 linear feet and 4 bound volume; 1956-1970) is a series that contains the correspondence, memos, statements, and the by-laws and charter of the beginning of OTS. The original material is in 4 bound volumes, and additional material is in folders. The bound material is organized chronologically, and the folders are alphabetically arranged.
  - Charter and By-Laws 1963-1972 (Box 3)
  - Committee on a Proposed Center for Tropical Studies (CENTROP) 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - History Summary undated (Box 3)
  - OTS Statements 1962-1970 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Proposal for CENTROP 1956-1959 (Box 3)
  - General 1958-1968, 4 volumes (Box 4)
- Financial Records 1958-1977
  The Financial Records (.5 linear feet; 1958-1977) series is composed of general financial operations, OTS debt, National Science Foundation grants, and member support material. It is organized alphabetically.
  - Charges for OTS Cost-Centers 1976 (Box 5)
  - Debt to MCOTS 1971-1973 (Box 5)
  - Field Station Use 1970 (Box 5)
  - Fiscal Year Budgets 1977 (Box 5)
  - Fund Raising 1974 (Box 5)
  - Funds Crisis 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Grants 1963, 1970-1972 (Box 5)
  - Individual Institution Fellowships 1973 (Box 5)
  - MCOTS Support in Dollars 1958 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Sea Grant 1977 (Box 5)
  - National Science Foundation 1965-1977 (Box 5)
  - Operations 1964-1972, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Task Force on the Organization and Financial Management of OTS 1976 (Box 5)
- Meetings Files 1963-1981
  The Meetings Files (1.5 linear feet; 1963-1981) series is largely made up of minutes, memos, and correspondences from meetings of the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee. The Board of Directors met annually and the Executive Committee met twice a year. This series is organized alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Advisory Council 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Annual Board of Directors 1963-1981, 16 folders (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee 1965-1971, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee 1971-1981, 12 folders (Box 6)
    - MCOTS Involvement 1965 (Box 6)
  - Regional 1972 (Box 6)
  - Tropical Biome 1971 (Box 6)
- Membership Records 1966-1977
  The Membership Records (.3 linear feet; 1966-1977) series is composed of lists of members. It includes member institutions, institution representation on the Board of Directors and Executive Committee. It is organized alphabetically.
  - Board of Directors 1966-1977 (Box 6)
  - Entry Correspondence 1970-1974 (Box 6)
  - General 1969-1977 (Box 6)
  - Institutions 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Officers and Executive Committee 1965-1967 (Box 6)
- Projects, Proposals, and Reports 1957-1977
  The Projects, Proposals, and Reports (.4 linear feet; 1957-1977) series is made up of three files: Projects, Proposals, and Reports. The Projects subseries contains information on projects which the organization was working on or planning. The Proposals file includes suggestions for future projects for OTS. The Reports series includes evaluation of OTS by individuals and institutions. This series and the files are organized alphabetically.
  - Projects
    - Caribbean Watershed 1975-1976 (Box 6)
    - Marine Resources in North West Costa Rica 1977 (Box 6)
    - Monte Lloyd 1976-1977 (Box 6)
    - Stingless Bee Communities 1971 (Box 6)
    - Tropical Biome 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Tropical Lowland Forest Communities undated (Box 6)
  - Proposals
    - Advances in Tropical Wood Science undated (Box 6)
    - Data Bank 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Planning for the Next Decade 1971 (Box 6)
  - Reports
    - Associate Director for Education 1970 (Box 6)
    - Costa Rica 1965 (Box 6)
    - El Salto, Guatemala 1966 (Box 6)
    - Executive Director 1965-1966 (Box 6)
    - Lancetilla, Honduras 1964-1966 (Box 6)
    - Marine Stations 1966 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Sea-Level Canal 1966 (Box 6)
    - Problems and Needs undated (Box 6)
    - Southwestern Research Station 1957 (Box 6)
    - Staff and Students 1965-1966 (Box 6)
- Topical Files 1948-1974
  The Topical Files (1.3 linear feet; 1948-1974) series is an alphabetical listing of OTS general organizational files. These records document decisions, debates, and processes of OTS. They contain information on conferences, workshops, field stations, and annual reports.
  - Annual Reports 1969-1971, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Benefits Program 1966 (Box 7)
  - Board of Directors Handbook 1969 (Box 7)
  - Central American Office (CAO) 1969-1971 (Box 7)
  - Conferences
    - Ecology of Development in Central America and Panama 1974 (Box 7)
    - Panama 1966 (Box 7)
  - Costa Rican National Council of Science and Technology (CONICIT) 1981 (Box 7)
  - Course Accreditation at Duke University 1970 (Box 7)
  - Dale Ingram, Inc. 1972 (Box 7)
  - Facilities and Equipment
    - General 1965-1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - La Selva 1973-1977 (Box 7)
    - Las Cruses 1970-1976 (Box 7)
    - Turrialba Station 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Statements of Interest in OTS (University of Michigan) undated (Box 7)
  - Families Associated with Field Courses 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Forest Types 1971 (Box 7)
  - International Biological Programs Corporation 1971 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Ecology 1970, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Job Applicants 1965-1975 (Box 7)
  - Latin America 1971 (Box 7)
  - Library Facilities 1967 (Box 7)
  - North American Office (NAO)
    - General Affairs 1968-1972 (Box 7)
    - Individual Institutions 1972 (Box 7)
    - Relocation 1968-1972 (Box 7)
  - Organizational Conflict 1971 (Box 7)
  - Policy
    - Collecting Services in Costa Rica 1968 (Box 7)
    - Evaluation of Student Applications 1971 (Box 7)
    - Pesticides 1970 (Box 7)
  - Program Statements 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Reference Book for OTS 1970 (Box 8)
  - Recruitment of Faculty and Students 1965 (Box 8)
  - Relations with Costa Rica 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Research 1967, 1971-1977 (Box 8)
  - Research Club Speech 1966 (Box 8)
  - Research in Mexico (University of Michigan) 1948 (Box 8)
  - Review Panel 1971 (Box 8)
  - Rules and Equipment 1967 (Box 8)
  - Snooperscopes (Infra-Red) 1965-1967 (Box 8)
  - Standard Fruit and Steamship Company 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - Structure of Ecosystems Program 1970 (Box 8)
  - Teas/Spencer Conflict 1969 (Box 8)
  - Universidad Centro Americana Managua, Nicaragua 1974 (Box 8)
  - Universidad de Costa Rica 1966-1974 (Box 8)
  - University of Michigan $55 Million Program 1966 (Box 8)
  - Workshop on Development and the Environment 1970-1971 (Box 8)
- Writings 1955-1977
  The Writings (.3 linear feet; 1955-1977) series includes drafts of publicity brochures, correspondence on a monograph series, and newsletters. Also included are some writings by various OTS faculty.
  - Brochures and Handbooks 1969-1972 (Box 8)
  - Monograph Series 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - News Articles 1967 (Box 8)
  - News Service 1967 (Box 8)
  - Newsletters 1968-1977 (Box 8)
  - OTS Faculty 1955-1970 (Box 8)
- Files from the office of Warren H. Wagner 1949-1972
  Files from the office of Warren H. Wagner (1.0 linear feet, 1949-1972) contain correspondence, course materials, materials from the National Science Foundation, a proposal for the establishment of a center for teaching and research in the isthmus of Tehuantepec (preliminary draft and supporting letters), OTS Executive Committee Meeting materials, and Annual Report of OTS (1969).
  - Letters to William Steere regarding his proposal for a tropical biological station 1949 (Box 9)
  - Course schedules and outlines 1966 (Box 9)
  - Request to National Science Foundation: "A continuing program of graduate education in tropical studies" 1972 (Box 9)
  - Proposal for the establishment of a center for teaching and research in the isthmus of Tehuantepec (preliminary draft and supporting letters) 1956-1956 (Box 9)
  - Basic References for OTS Executive Committee Meeting
    - April 9-10, 1970 (Box 9)
    - June 15-16, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Annual Report of OTS 1969, 2 volumes (Box 9)
  - Published and miscellaneous (Box 9)
- Organizing Committee 1949-1963
  The Organizing Committee (1 linear foot, 1949-1963) series includes early drafts of the constitution and by-laws, correspondence, planning committee notes, Tropical Center development materials; reports (1958-1963; 4 folders), occasional papers, research papers, official lists of tropical plants and animals; proposal for a Coordinated Research Program in Mexico, Tehuantepec Report (revised), surveys, materials from survey-trips to Mexico, maps, physical plant estimated costs, National Referral Center for Science and Technology, newsletters, brochures, and other (affiliated) institutions. The materials are primarily in English, though is a significant quantity of Spanish language materials. Mexico was the initial site for the proposed field station. Costa Rica, in the end, was the home of the field station. This series is useful for background information for the Organization for Tropical Studies. Marginalia notes on correspondence, meeting notes, and planning documents lend insight into the organizing process. Personal correspondence as well as official committee documents reveal the successes and frustrations of organizing an international, tropical field station.
  - Constitution and By-Laws 1950-1962 (Box 10)
  - Letter of Authorization June 27, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1958, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1959 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1960-1963 (Box 10)
  - Meeting Notes, 1958, 1962-1963 (Box 10)
  - Planning Committee Notes, Handwritten (Box 10)
  - Notes on Tropical Center Development 1959, 1960 (Box 10)
  - Reports 1958 (Box 10)
  - Reports 1959 (Box 10)
  - Reports 1960, 1962 (Box 10)
  - Reports 1963 (Box 10)
  - Occasional Papers 1956-1962 (Box 10)
  - Research Papers 1957-1962 (Box 10)
  - Official Lists of Tropical Plants and Animals 1959-1962 (Box 10)
  - Coordinated Program for Research in Mexico 1948-1949 (Box 10)
  - Tehuantepec Report, revised July 18, 1957 (Box 10)
  - Survey, "Work Not Related to Tehuantepec," 1957 (Box 10)
  - Surveys for Interest in Tehuantepec, Mexico Project 1957 (Box 10)
  - Hartweg's Trip to Mexico July-September 1959 (Box 10)
  - Maps (Box 10)
  - Estimates of Cost for Physical Plant 1959 (Box 10)
  - Proposal for Water Purification Plant (Box 10)
  - National Referral Center for Science and Technology 1962-1963 (Box 10)
  - Brochures 1952-1953, 1962 (Box 10)
  - Caribbean Group Services Newsletters 1958-1959 (Box 10)
  - Rancho Del Cielo Newsletters December 5, 1955 (Box 10)
  - Villa Jones 1958, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Other Institutions (Box 10)